Register of the Ivan Alekseevich Kurganov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
I. A. Kurganov papers,
1940-1980
2001C74
Kurganov, I. A. (Ivan Alekseevich)
27 manuscript boxes, 3 card file boxes (12.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, card files, and printed matter, relating to economics, anti-communist movements, and Russian émigré affairs. Includes records of the Koordinatsionnyi TSentr Antibol'shevistskoi Bor'by and some papers of Aleksandr Kerensky.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired in 2001.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1895, January 14 Born, Russia
1914-1920 Officer in the Russian Imperial Army during World War I and served with the anti-Bolshevik forces under Admiral Kolchak in Siberia. Captured by the Red Army, imprisoned and eventually released
1924-1930 Lectured at Leningrad University
1930-1942 Lectured at the Leningrad Financial-Economic Institute
1934 Became Professor of Economics
1935-1941 Held chair at the Institute of Soviet Cooperative Trade in Moscow
1939 Ph.D. in Economics
1942 Evacuated from Leningrad with the Financial-Economic Institute to the North Caucasus
1943 Arrived in Berlin, Germany
1950 Emigrated to the United States
1951-1956 Held a leading position and presided over the Coordinating Center of Anti-Bolshevik Struggle
1958 Author, Reformizm v SSSR, Sel'skoe khoziaistvo na novom etape, Sovremennoe polozhenie vlasti v SSSR
1961 Author, Natsii SSSR i russkii vopros
1967 Author, Sem'ia v SSSR, 1917-1967
1968 Author, Zhenshchiny i kommunizm
1971 Author, Women in the USSR
1980 Died
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ivan Alekseevich Kurganov, acquired in 2001, consist of correspondence, published and unpublished writings, including manuscripts of books and articles, reports, and memoranda. These materials document the political and intellectual life of Professor Kurganov and his contemporaries from the early 1950s through the late 1970s. Kurganov's associates included well-known Russian émigrés such as Sergei P. Mel'gunov, Mikhail Karpovich, V. Orekhov, Vladmir Samarin, and many others. The most important correspondent was Alexander Kerensky.
After World War II, Kurganov worked as a journalist for the Russian émigré press. His work as a journalist is reflected in the speeches and writings series. Between the years 1959 and 1980 Professor Kurganov published several books, and many articles and pamphlets, also included in the series.
Included in the Kurganov collection are the records of the Coordinating Center of Anti-Bolshevik Struggle (Munich), which sought to unify the political activities of various anti-Soviet Russian émigré organizations. From 1951 to 1956, Professor Kurganov held a leading position in and later presided over the Center. During this time, he worked closely with Alexander Kerensky and Sergei P. Mel'gunov. The records of the Coordinating Center provide a wealth of information on anti-Soviet activities in the Russian émigré community during the 1950s. Of great interest are Alexander Kerensky's letters on his anti-Soviet political activities, relations with a new generation of Russian émigrés (displaced persons), and his stance on many other issues.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Anti-communist movements.; Russians--Germany.; Communism.; Economics.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Germany.
Occupations
Economists.
Other Index Terms Related to this Collection
Kerensky, Aleksandr Fyodorovich, 1881-1970.; Koordinatsionnyi tsentr antibol'shevistskoi bor'by.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1940-1996. (Box 1)
  Certificates, curriculum vitae, books, identification cards, immigration documents, and other materials relating to the life and career of I. A. Kurganov
- Correspondence, 1943-1980. (Box 1-4)
  Letters to and from various individuals and organizations. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1945-1976. (Box 4-14)
  Book manuscripts, essays, reports, studies, speeches, and other writings by I. A. Kurganov. Arranged chronologically by title
- Koordinatsionnyi Tsentr Anti-Bol'shevistskoi Bor'by (Coordinating Center of Anti-Bolshevik Struggle), 1948-1980. (Box 15-21)
  Announcement, clippings, correspondence, reports, and subject file relating to the activities of the Koordinatsionnyi Tsentr, collected by I. A. Kurganov. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Writings by Others, 1917-1974. (Box 21-24)
  Typescripts and printed copies of writings by authors associated with I. A. Kurganov. Arranged alphabetically by name of author
- Clippings, 1949-1980. (Box 24-27)
  Clippings from various newspapers, serials, and other printed publications, relating to events and conditions in the Soviet Union, the Russian emigration in Europe and the United States, collected by I. A. Kurganov for his research. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- Card File, n.d. (Box 28-30)
  Reference cards to sources relating to a variety of subjects used by I. A. Kurganov for his research
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1940-1996 (Box 1)
  - Certificates of academic standing and organizational status, 1940-1957 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Curriculum vitae, n.d. (Folder 1: 2)
  - Family file - Neratova, Rimma (daughter)
    - V dni voiny: Semeinaia khronika, St. Petersburg, 1996 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Politicheskaia ekonomiia, Akademiia Nauk SSSR, Institut Ekonomiki, Moscow, 1954. (Folder 1: 4)
      Inserted note by Rimma Neratova regarding I. A. Kurganov as being chief editor of this book
  - Identification cards, 1957-1961 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Immigration documents to the United States, 1950 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 7)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1943-1980
  - General
    - Correspondence with various publishers
      - 1957-1968 (Folder 1: 8)
      - 1969-1974 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Letters from various libraries and organizations ordering books by I. A. Kurganov, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Unidentified
    - General, 1957-1974 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Anatolii Vasil'evich, 1958-1972 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Fedor Ivanovich, 1966-1974 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Georgii Al'bertovich, 1961 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Gerhard Berngardovich, 1958 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Igor Arturovich, 1962 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Iurii Pavlovich, 1964 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Izrail' Grigor'evich, 1968 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Mikhail Vasil'evich, 1970 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Mikhail Vladimirovich, 1971 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Nikolai Ivanovich, 1972 (Folder 2: 12)
    - Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1969-1972 (Folder 2: 13)
    - Sergei Evgen'evich, 1961 (Folder 2: 14)
    - Valentina Konstantinovna, 1974 (Folder 2: 15)
    - Vladimir Dimitrievich, 1971 (Folder 2: 16)
    - Vladimir Ivanovich, 1971 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Vladimir Sergeevich, 1969-1970 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1970 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Afanasieff, V., 1962 (Folder 2: 20)
  - American Committee for Liberation, 1962 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Anatolii, A., n.d. (Folder 2: 22)
  - Argus, Mikhail K., 1969 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Arnol'd, Fedor T., 1961 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Aronson, Grigorii, 1967-1968 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Artemov, Aleksandr, 1962-1973 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Association of Russian-American Scholars in the United States of America (Konstantin G. Belousov), 1971-1975 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Avtorkhanov, Aleksandr A., 1961-1972 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Bakhmeteff, B. A., n.d. (Folder 2: 29)
  - Balakshin, Aleksandr N., 1970-1973 (Folder 2: 30)
  - Balmashev, Mikhail V., 1962-1978 (Folder 2: 31)
  - Barmin, Aleksandr G., 1971-1973 (Folder 2: 32)
  - Baxter, Ian, 1971 (Folder 2: 33)
  - Belopol'skii, A., 1961 (Folder 2: 34)
  - Belosel'skii-Belozerskii, Sergei S., 1961-1966 (Folder 2: 35)
  - Berezhetskii, G., n.d. (Folder 2: 36)
  - Bilimovich, Aleksandr D., 1961 (Folder 2: 37)
  - Bobrinskii, A., 1958 (Folder 2: 38)
  - Bodleian Library, Oxford University, 1970 (Folder 2: 39)
  - Bogatyrchuk, Fedor P., 1961-1972 (Folder 2: 40)
  - Boldyrev, Konstantin V., 1967-1972 (Folder 2: 41)
  - Bol'shukhin, Iurii, 1961-62 (Folder 2: 42)
  - Borman, Arkadii, 1971 (Folder 2: 43)
  - Budanov, Iakov V., 1967-1973 (Folder 2: 44)
  - Central Association of Political Emigrants from the USSR (Munich), 1961 (Folder 2: 45)
  - Dallin, David, 1957 (Folder 2: 46)
  - De Bransbourgh, Wadim, 1965 (Folder 2: 47)
  - Deriuzhinskaia, Nataliia S., 1968 (Folder 2: 48)
  - Dmitrieva, Elena, 1972 (Folder 2: 49)
  - Dneprov, Andrei P., 1957-1958 (Folder 2: 50)
  - Domogatskii, Boris S., 1967 (Folder 2: 51)
  - Ermolaev, G., 1968 (Folder 2: 52)
  - Fillipov, Boris A., 1967-1973 (Folder 2: 53)
  - Fon-Lampe, A. A., 1958 (Folder 2: 54)
  - Fotiev, Kirill, 1973 (Folder 2: 55)
  - Four Continent Book Corporation, 1969-1971 (Folder 2: 56)
  - Galai, Nikolai, 1960-1963 (Folder 2: 57)
  - Garanin, Evgenii I., 1973 (Folder 2: 58)
  - Gintse, D. M., 1974 (Folder 2: 59)
  - Gol'dvin, F. I., 1971-1972 (Folder 2: 60)
  - Guins, George, 1968 (Folder 2: 61)
  - Ialymova, Maria N., 1961 (Folder 2: 62)
  - Institute of Political Psychology in Communist Studies, Brooklyn, New York, 1961 (Folder 2: 63)
  - Iurasov, Vladimir I., 1969 (Folder 2: 64)
  - Karpovich, Mikhail M., 1958 (Folder 2: 65)
  - Kerensky, Alexander
    - 1953-1954 (Folder 2: 66)
    - 1955-1960 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Khomiakov, Gennadii A., 1961-1967 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Kiselev, Aleksandr, 1969-1973 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Kishner, Andrei L., 1958 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Kongress za prava i svobodu v Rossii, 1957 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Konstantinovskii, Boris A., 1972 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Kovalev, D., n.d. (Folder 3: 7)
  - Krestinskaia, M., 1962-1967 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Kungurtsev, Vadim A., 1963 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Kuz'mov, Ivan, 1944 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Kuznetsov, Anatolii, n.d. (Folder 3: 11)
  - Lebedev, F., 1961 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Lermolo, Mikhail P., 1970-1974 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Levchenko, Vladimir A., 1957-1958 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Losskii, N., 1959 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Maiorova, Ekaterina I., 1965 (Folder 3: 16)
  - Maksimov, Nikolai M., 1958 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Mansyrev, Mr., 1964 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Marin, Iu., 1972 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Martianov, Nikolai N., 1967-1968 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Mel'gunov, Sergei P., 1954-1955 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Mikhailovskii, Anatolii I., 1962 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Morschen, N., n.d. (Folder 3: 23)
  - Narokov, Nikolai V., 1955-1969 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Natov, Anatol, 1968 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Nicolaevsky, Boris, n.d. (Folder 3: 26)
  - Novoe russkoe slovo (A. Poliakov), 1962-1974 (Folder 3: 27)
  - Obol'ianina, Sof'ia A., 1968 (Folder 3: 28)
  - Okolovich, Georgii S., 1967-1968 (Folder 3: 29)
  - Orekhov, Vasilii V., 1961-1972 (Folder 3: 30)
  - Osipov, Nikolai I., 1961 (Folder 3: 31)
  - Ostrovskaia, Evgeniia A., 1962-1965 (Folder 3: 32)
  - Ostrovskii, Evgenii R., 1961-1972 (Folder 3: 33)
  - Pashin, Nikolai S., 1955-1974 (Folder 3: 34)
  - Perekrestov, Oleg V., 1972-1974 (Folder 3: 35)
  - Perov, Nikolai, 1971-1972 (Folder 3: 36)
  - Petrov, Pavel, 1964 (Folder 3: 37)
  - Pirozhkova, Vera A., 1969 (Folder 3: 38)
  - Poltoratzky, Nikolai, 1967 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Pomerantsev, Nikolai P., 1967 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Poremskaia, T., 1961 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Poremskii, Vladimir D., 1967-1973 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Posev (Frankfurt), 1970-1974 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Pozdniakova, Nina S., 1974 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Pushkarev, Sergei G., 1964-1972 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Radlova, Maria G., n.d. (Folder 4: 8)
  - Rafal'skii, Sergei M., 1970 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Rar, Gleb A., 1974 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Rar, Lev A., 1974 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Rod, A., 1958 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Rossiia (New York), 1970-1971 (Folder 4: 13)
  - Rostow, Mr., 1963 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Roy, V. S., 1972 (Folder 4: 15)
  - Rozhdestvenskii, Serafim P., 1969-1973 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Russian Émigré Society of Boston, 1966 (Folder 4: 17)
  - Russkaia Akademicheskaia Gruppa v SShA, 1970 (Folder 4: 18)
  - Russkii Obshchevoinskii Soiuz, 1967 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Sabov, Suvans, 1971 (Folder 4: 20)
  - Saint Seraphim's Foundation, 1970-1973 (Folder 4: 21)
  - Sedykh, Andrei, 1974 (Folder 4: 22)
  - Sergievskii, Boris, 1958 (Folder 4: 23)
  - Shalakhovskii, P., n.d. (Folder 4: 24)
  - Shefler, L., 1972 (Folder 4: 25)
  - Sheglovskii, Valentin, 1973 (Folder 4: 26)
  - Shimanovskaia, V., 1974 (Folder 4: 27)
  - Shtam, Grigorii, n.d. (Folder 4: 28)
  - Shteppa, Valentina, 1961 (Folder 4: 29)
  - Skriabina, Elena A., 1971-1972 (Folder 4: 30)
  - Skriabina, Raia, 1972 (Folder 4: 31)
  - Slavonic Bazaar, 1969 (Folder 4: 32)
  - Sokolov, V., 1980 (Folder 4: 33)
  - Srechinskii, Iurii S., 1969-1971 (Folder 4: 34)
  - Stolypin, Arkadii, 1972 (Folder 4: 35)
  - Struve, Petr B., 1943 (Folder 4: 36)
  - Svet, Gershon, 1961 (Folder 4: 37)
  - Svetlanin, Andrei V., 1961-1965 (Folder 4: 38)
  - Svoboda (Jersey City), 1961 (Folder 4: 39)
  - Svobodnaia Rossiia, 1972 (Folder 4: 40)
  - Swoboda (Munich), 1958 (Folder 4: 41)
  - Tarasova, Nataliia B., 1972 (Folder 4: 42)
  - Taylor, Pauline B., 1968 (Folder 4: 43)
  - Timashev, Nikolai S., 1961 (Folder 4: 44)
  - Tolstoy, Alexandra L., n.d. (Folder 4: 45)
  - Ul'ianov, Nikolai I., 1961-1970 (Folder 4: 46)
  - Ul'ianova, Nataliia, 1972 (Folder 4: 47)
  - Veinbaum, Mark E., 1965-1972 (Folder 4: 48)
  - Viktor Kamkin Bookstore, 1967-1980 (Folder 4: 49)
  - Volga Bookstore, 1970 (Folder 4: 50)
  - Volianskaia, Liudmila, 1974-1975 (Folder 4: 51)
  - Vol'skii, Nikolai, 1949 (Folder 4: 52)
  - Weil, Boris, 1980 (Folder 4: 53)
  - Zavalishin, Viacheslav K., 1970-1972 (Folder 4: 54)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1945-1976
  - General
    - Miscellaneous drafts and notes, n.d. (Folder 4: 55)
    - Printed copies of articles from various publications
      - 1948-1958 (Folder 4: 56)
      - 1960-1972 (Folder 4: 57)
    - Titles, outlines, and tables of contents of selected writings by I. A. Kurganov, n.d. (Box-folder 5: 1)
      Holographs and typescripts
  - "Berlinskie siluety," n.d. (Folder 5: 2)
    Typescript
  - "Bibliografiia," n.d. (Folder 5: 3)
    Holograph
  - "Biografiia I. A. Kurganova, izlozhennaia im samim," n.d. (Folder 5: 4)
  - "Bitva za khleb," n.d. (Folder 5: 5)
  - "Burzhuaznaia intelligentsiia," n.d. (Folder 5: 6-7)
    Research materials, holograph, and typescript
  - "Communist Strategy for World Domination," n.d. (Folder 5: 8)
  - "Deti v SSSR," n.d. (Folder 5: 9)
  - "Diplomaticheskie epizody," n.d. (Folder 5: 10)
  - "Dogovor Stalina i Gitlera," n.d. (Folder 5: 11-12)
    Research materials, notes, holograph, and typescript
  - "Doktriny," n.d. (Folder 6: 1-2)
    Research notes, holograph, and typescript
  - "Ekonomicheskoe nastuplenie kommunizma," n.d. (Folder 6: 3)
  - "Ekonomika i russkii vopros," n.d. (Folder 6: 4)
    Holograph and clippings
  - "Ekonomika kapitalizma," n.d. (Folder 6: 5)
  - "Evropa, diplomatiia, strategiia," n.d. (Folder 6: 6)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Faktory i kommunisticheskaia revoliutsiia v Rossii," n.d. (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Filosofiia i politika SSSR," n.d. (Folder 6: 8-9)
  - "Golgofa rossiiskogo naroda," n.d. (Folder 6: 10)
  - "Ideologiia kolonializma," n.d. (Folder 6: 11)
  - "Inostrannye uchastniki kommunisticheskoi revoliutsii v Rossii," n.d. (Folder 6: 12)
    Printed copy
  - "K perspektive," n.d. (Box-folder 7: 1)
    Research notes and holograph
  - "K strategii," n.d. (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Kazakhstan," n.d. (Folder 7: 3-4)
  - "Khristianstvo i politika," n.d. (Folder 7: 5)
  - "Klassovaia struktura sovetskogo obshchestva," n.d. (Folder 7: 6)
  - "Klassy," n.d. (Folder 7: 7)
  - "Klassy v SSSR," n.d.
    - "Burzhuaziia." (Folder 7: 8)
    - "Intelligentsiia." (Folder 7: 9)
    - "Rabochii klass." (Folder 7: 10)
    - "Teoriia." (Folder 7: 11)
  - "Kommunisticheskie metody perestroiki obhshchestva," n.d. (Folder 7: 12)
  - "Kommunizm i diplomatiia," n.d. (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - "KPK i KPSS - Doktrina Mao," n.d. (Folder 8: 2)
  - "Migratsiia i dvizhenie Rossii na vostok," n.d. (Folder 8: 3)
  - "Molchalivoe bol'shinstvo," n.d. (Folder 8: 4)
  - "Narodniki," n.d. (Folder 8: 5)
    Holograph. Includes clippings relating to this subject
  - "Nine Questions," n.d. (Folder 8: 6)
  - "Obshchestvo, partiia, natsii, raznoe," n.d. (Folder 8: 7)
  - "Pereselenie krest'ian v Rossii," n.d (Folder 8: 8)
  - "Pobeda menshinstva," n.d. (Folder 8: 9)
  - "Port Artur," n.d. (Folder 8: 10)
  - "Prichiny i revoliutsiia v Rossii," n.d. (Folder 8: 11)
  - "Religiia," n.d. (Folder 8: 12)
  - "Rossiia pered I-oi mirovoi voinoi i revoliutsiei," n.d. (Folder 8: 13)
  - "Russkii vopros - Strategiia kommunizma v bor'be za mirovoe gospodstvo," n.d. (Folder 8: 14)
  - "Sbornik statei," n.d. (Folder 8: 15)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Sem'ia i deti," n.d. (Folder 9: 1)
  - "Sovetskii narod - Kollektivizm," n.d. (Folder 9: 2)
  - "Sovremennaia strategiia kommunizma," n.d. (Folder 9: 3)
  - "SSSR i Pol'sha," n.d.
    - Holograph (Folder 9: 4)
    - Typescript (Folder 9: 5-6)
  - "Statistika," n.d. (Folder 9: 7)
  - "Strategiia kommunizma," n.d. (Folder 9: 8)
  - "Strategiia voennoi ekonomiki," n.d. (Folder 9: 9)
  - "Ves' mir na koleniakh," n.d. (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - "Vypiska iz knigi Vitte Vospominaniia (o Mendeleeve), n.d. (Folder 10: 2)
  - "SSSR," Emden, Germany, 1945. (Folder 10: 3)
  - "SSSR v epokhu voin i revoliutsii," 1946-1947. (Folder 10: 4)
  - "Christianity and Politics," 1947. (Folder 10: 5)
  - "Velikaia bor'ba dvukh system mira," 1948. (Folder 10: 6)
  - "Prinuditel'nyi detskii trud v SSSR ili gosudarstvennye trudovye resursy," 1950. (Folder 10: 7)
  - "The National Problem in the Soviet Union," The Russian Review, 1951, volume 10, no. 4. (Folder 10: 8)
  - "Natsionalnaia problema v Rossii," Novyi zhurnal (New York), 1951, Volume XXV. (Folder 10: 9)
  - "Vtoromu plenumu piati rossiiskikh organizatsii," report, Wiesbaden, Germany, 1951. (Folder 10: 10)
  - "Krest'ianstvo v Rossii," Sud'by Rossii (New York), 1957, no. 1. (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - "Emigratsiia i Kongress za prava i svobodu v Rossii," 1975 September 16. (Folder 11: 2)
  - "O Reformizme i narodnykh trebovaniakh," 1958. (Folder 11: 3)
    Printed copy. Includes correspondence, notes, and press reviews relating to this and other related works by I. A. Kurganov
  - "KPSS - Doklad o sovremmenom polozhenii vlasti v SSSR," Kongress za prava i svobodu v Rossii, The Hague, 1958 April 25. (Folder 11: 4)
  - Report to the 10th Conference of the Institute for the Study of the USSR, Munich, 1958 July 25. (Folder 11: 5)
  - "Reformizm v SSSR," Informatsionnyi biulleten' Komiteta za prava i svobodu v Rossii, 1958 July/September. (Folder 11: 6)
  - "Perekhodnyi period mirovoi istorii," Posev, 1960, no. 41/42. (Folder 11: 7)
    Clippings
  - "Sovremennaia strategiia kommunizma," Nashi dni (Frankfurt am Main), 1960, no. 2. (Folder 11: 8)
  - "Ekonomika SSSR v natsional'nom razreze," Nashi Dni (Frankfurt am Main), 1960, no. 7. (Folder 11: 9)
  - Natsii SSSR i russkii vopros, Frankfurt/Main, 1961
    - Printed copy (Folder 11: 10)
    - Press reviews, 1961-1962 (Folder 11: 11)
    - Press reviews, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - "Strategiia kommunizma," report to the Committee for Rights and Freedom in Russia, Paris, 1961 March 26. (Folder 12: 2)
  - "Ekonomika i russkii vopros: O knige professora V. V. Rostou Stadii ekonomicheskogo rosta," 1962 November. (Folder 12: 3)
  - "Sotsialisticheskie gosudarstva i natsional-kommunizm," Mosty (Munich), 1963, no. 10. (Folder 12: 4)
  - "Tri tsifry," Novoe russkoe slovo (New York), 1964 December 12. (Folder 12: 5)
  - "Pereselenie krest'ian v Rossii," Grani (Frankfurt/Main), 1965 June. (Folder 12: 6)
  - "Demograficheskaia katastrofa," Novoe russkoe slovo (New York), 1965 September. (Folder 12: 7)
  - "Kommunisticheskaia revoliutsiia v Rossii," Grani (Frankfurt/Main), no. 63, 1967. (Folder 12: 8)
  - "Kommunisticheskie metody perestroiki obshchestva," Grani (Frankfurt/Main), no. 64, 1967. (Folder 12: 9)
  - Sem'ia v SSSR, New York, 1967
    - Correspondence, 1961-1967 (Folder 12: 10)
    - Printed copy, 1967 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - Correspondence and press reviews, 1967-1968 (Folder 13: 2)
  - "Kapitalizm i klassovaia teoriia Marksa," Posev (Frankfurt/Main), no. 2, 1968. (Folder 13: 3)
    Holograph, typescript, and printed copy
  - Zhenshchiny i kommunizm, New York, 1968
    - Correspondence
      - 1962-1970 (Folder 13: 4)
      - 1969-1974 (Folder 13: 5)
    - Correspondence and press reviews, 1968-1969 (Folder 13: 6)
    - Typescript (Folder 13: 7-8)
    - Galley proof with annotations (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - Printed copy (Folder 14: 2)
  - "Inostrannye uchastniki kommunisticheskoi revoliutsii v Rossii," Zapiski russkoi akademicheskoi gruppy v SSHA, New York, volume IV, 1970. (Folder 14: 3)
  - "Interv'iu dannoe I. A. Kurganovym," 1970 September. (Folder 14: 4)
  - Women in the USSR, London/Ontario, 1971
    - Printed copy (Folder 14: 5)
    - Correspondence and press reviews, 1971-1972 (Folder 14: 6)
  - "Khrushchev i destalinizatsiia," Posev (Frankfurt/Main), 1971 November. (Folder 14: 7)
  - "Inostrantsy v russkoi revoliutsii," Posev (Frankfurt/Main), 1972 April. (Folder 14: 8)
  - "Sovetsko-pol'skaia voina 1920g.," Zapiski russkoi akademicheskoi gruppy v SSHA, New York, Volume X, 1976. (Folder 14: 9)
- KOORDINATSIONNYI TSENTR ANTI-BOL'SHEVISTSKOI BOR'BY (Coordinating Center of Anti-Bolshevik Struggle), 1948-1980 (Box 15)
  - General
    - 1949-1951 (Folder 15: 1)
    - 1954 (Folder 15: 2)
    - 1955 (Folder 15: 3)
  - Announcement of establishment of the Center, Munich, 1952 September 16 (Folder 15: 4)
  - Bulletin. Vestnik koordinatsionnogo tsentra antibol'shevistskoi bor'by (Munich), no. 2, 1953 September (Folder 15: 5)
  - Clippings
    - 1953 (Folder 15: 6)
    - 1953-1954 (Folder 15: 7)
    - 1955 (Folder 15: 8)
    - 1955-1956 (Folder 15: 9)
    - 1956 (Folder 15: 10)
  - Correspondence (Box 16)
    - General, 1955-1956 (Folder 16: 1)
    - Kerensky, Alexander
      - 1951-1952 (Folder 16: 2)
      - 1952 (Folder 16: 3)
      - 1952-1955 (Folder 16: 4)
      - 1953-1955 (Folder 16: 5)
      - 1953-1957 (Folder 16: 6)
      - 1955 (Folder 16: 7-8)
      - 1956 (Box-folder 17: 1)
      - 1958-1960 (Folder 17: 2)
      - 1961-1966 (Folder 17: 3)
    - Komitet za prava i svobodu v Rossii
      - 1957-1958 (Folder 17: 4)
      - 1957-1962 (Folder 17: 5)
    - Mel'gunov, Sergei P.
      - 1952-1954 (Folder 17: 6)
      - 1954 (Folder 17: 7)
    - Pozdniakov, Vladimir V.
      - 1961-1969 (Folder 17: 8)
      - 1970-1973 (Box-folder 18: 1)
    - Rossiiskoe narodnoe dvizhenie
      - 1948-1951 (Folder 18: 2)
      - 1952 (Folder 18: 3-6)
      - 1953 (Folder 18: 7)
    - Samarin, Vladimir D. (Box 19)
      - 1961-1968 (Folder 19: 1)
      - 1969-1972 (Folder 19: 2)
      - 1973-1980 (Folder 19: 3)
  - Reports
    - 1953 (Folder 19: 4)
    - 1953-1954 (Folder 19: 5)
    - 1954 (Folder 20: 1)
    - 1954-1955 (Folder 20: 2)
  - Subject file
    - Gul', Roman, 1949-1952 (Folder 20: 3)
    - Rossiiskoe narodnoe dvizhenie
      - General
        - 1948-1951 (Folder 20: 4)
        - 1951-1957 (Folder 20: 5)
      - Za Svobodu (Munich), 1952-1953 (Folder 20: 6)
    - Sud'by Rossii (New York), 1955-1957 (Folder 20: 7)
    - Sud'by Rossii (New York), 1955-1957 (Box-folder 21: 1)
    - Wiesbaden Conference, 1951 November
      - General (Folder 21: 2)
      - Stenographic reports of meetings (Folder 21: 3-5)
- WRITINGS BY OTHERS, 1917-1974
  - Artem'ev, Viacheslav, 1956 (Folder 21: 6)
  - Avtorkhanov, A., 1951 (Folder 21: 7)
  - Bilimovich, A. D., 1955-1960 (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - Chernov, Victor, n.d. (Folder 22: 2)
  - Fedorov, L., n.d. (Folder 22: 3)
  - Filipov, Boris, 1969-1974 (Folder 22: 4)
  - Jasny, Naum, 1951 (Folder 22: 5)